<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Free Play]]></title>
  <link href="http://jrowdev.com//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jrowdev.com//"/>
  <updated>2012-10-04T16:40:24-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jrowdev.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Josh Rowley]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello world]]></title>
    <link href="http://jrowdev.com//blog/2012/10/04/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-04T12:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jrowdev.com//blog/2012/10/04/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello World</p>

<p>Hi everyone, my name is Josh Rowley, and I’m a student at the newly created Flatiron School. It’s been two days since we started, and I’ve already felt that I’ve gained more understanding of web development in the past two days then any of the self study I did before I started in the months leading up to it.</p>

<p>The most helpful thing to have in order to learn how to code, at least for me, is to be working with a group with the same goals and mission as yourself. That’s what we have here at the school. It also allows us to work in more realistic environment. The benefits of learning in a team for a beginner cannot be understated. Everyone has different strengths and thought processes, and putting them together helps us solve the challenges of development in faster and newer ways.</p>

<p>Of course, working in the school has also presented its own challenges compared to self study. I thought I knew git pretty well from studying previously and working on my own projects, but I had never actually used it to collaborate on a project with anyone else.</p>

<p>Day one, Avi had us create profile pages for the school website with HTML and CSS. Sounds simple enough, but we were all going to do it at the same time using the same github repo, by forking and creating our own feature branches. At the end, we were going to merge all of our separate work back into the master branch.</p>

<p>We were divided into teams of four, and we started to plan our workflow and collaborate on how the HTML layouts and CSS styling would look like. We thought we had a handle on how git worked, but after a couple of hours, we had way too many branches with common files spread out across our disparate local git repos with different versions across all of them. It was a mess, and we realized that we were a bit ambitious for the first day.</p>

<p>It also showed me that the biggest thing that I’m going to learn here is being able to work as a team on software. Avi emphasized this point several times and it was quite obvious after our first day that that was the case. Being able to communicate and be on the same page for workflow and planning is critical and I’m excited to learn these skills here. It’s definitely something that cannot be learned on your own.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
